<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A salutation of my endeared love in God's holy fear and dread, and for the clearing of my conscience, once more unto you of that city of Bristol ...</title>
            <author>Stirredge, Elizabeth, 1634-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5685A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2646:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A salutation of my endeared love in God's holy fear and dread, and for the clearing of my conscience, once more unto you of that city of Bristol ...</title>
                  <author>Stirredge, Elizabeth, 1634-1706.</author>
                  <author>Dole, Dorcas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Andrew Sowle?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 6: Elizabeth Stirredge ... 1683.</note>
                  <note>"To you that have been professors of the truth of God in the city of Bristol ..., p. 7-11, signed Dorcas Dole, 1683.</note>
                  <note>"O Lord! by a high hand ..." p. 12, signed: D.D.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement in colophon reads: Printed and sold by Andrew Sowle.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172725:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A <hi>SALUTATION</hi> of my Endeared Love in God's holy Fear and Dread, and for the clearing of my Conſcience, once more unto you of that City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> amongſt whom my Soul hath ſome Years travelled under many a dreadful Exerciſe, which hath made my Bones to ſhake, and my Heart to tremble before the great God of Heaven and Earth, who will yet further bring his notable Day, wherein all Fleſh ſhall Tremble before him.</head>
            <p>ANd now in the ſence of the great Love of God that hath been extended unto you of that City continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, firſt, in ſending of his Servants amongſt you, and endued them with Power from on High, that it wrought effectually upon many, whereby many are brought out of <hi>Egypts</hi> Darkneſs, and through the Red-Sea ſpiritually, and could ſing to the Lord, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did, when the Lord had wrought wonderfully for their deliverance, and by a high Hand and a wonderful Power brought them forth: And bleſſed be the Lord God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and honoured be his worthy Name, and the right Arm of his ſtrength, there are many living Witneſſes of theſe things in this our day: Oh, <hi>dear Friends!</hi> forget it not, but dwell low in the ſence of your deplorable ſtates that you were in, when firſt the Lord reached unto you, and opened that Eye in you, that let you ſee you were undone forever, if the Lord did not ariſe for your Deliverance, when many cryed out, <hi>for a Saviour, or elſe I periſh forever.</hi> Oh Friends! what was too dear for us to part with in that day for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172725:2"/>Lord? Truly can my Soul ſay, <hi>That all that ever my Eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, was nothing to me in compariſon to my Souls Redemption;</hi> Oh! it was precious in my Eve, and to this very day the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving remembrance of it dwells freſh upon my Spirit at this time, and my Heart and Soul loveth the Lord, and bleſſeth his worthy Name forever, and for evermore. And now the Lord is remembring the Covenant that many made with him in the dayes of their diſtreſs: Oh! remember, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to pay your Vows to the Lord; and look into your Hearts this day, and with the Light of the Lord ſearch and ſee, whether you are in Covenant this day with the Lord or no? If you are, ſurely you are not this day to ſerve your ſelves, but the living God, that made you for a purpoſe of his own Glory, and redeemed you with his precious Blood.</p>
            <p>And now conſider, you that are at eaſe in your <hi>Sion,</hi> and eating, and drinking, and wearing what ſeemeth deſirable in your own Eyes, notwithſtanding the Honour of the Lord lies engaged, and your Souls in great danger, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord diſtreſſed in your behalf: Oh! for the Lord's ſake, and for your own Souls ſake, that will periſh, if you do not ſpeedily Repent, and ariſe and ſtrip your ſelves, and ſhake your ſelves from theſe things, and come away, while the <hi>Call of the Lord</hi> laſteth; Oh! linger not, for the Day of the Lord haſteneth mightily, let nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you, make no excuſes any longer, leſt you be excluded out of God's Kingdom, and the Door be ſhut againſt you; Oh! think upon it, before the Mid-night Cry come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not one Day more will be afforded to work for the Lord: Oh then! Wife nor Children, Lands nor Livings, Husband nor Trade, Gold nor Silver will redeem one Soul; then that doleful Sentence will be ſounded, <hi>Depart, ye curſed workers of Iniquity, into everlaſting Torment, prepared for the Devil &amp; his Angels.</hi> Oh the ſenſe of theſe things lie <hi>very heavy</hi> upon my Spirit, and truly bows my Heart in Reverence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and Morning and Evening is my Heart afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, inſomuch that I can ſay, as the Prophet ſaid, <hi>Oh! that my Head were as Water, and mine Eyes as a Fountain of Tears, that I might Weep day and night, for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithful, that my
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172725:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>Spirit might be eaſed:</hi> For truly, Friends, though I am the leaſt amongſt many Thouſands of the Lord's People, and a weak Inſtrument, yet my Soul is concerned this day, and my Prayers to the great God of Heaven and Earth are, <hi>That he would be pleaſed again to ariſe, and utter his Voice, and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Alarm from his holy Habitation, and make the Hearts of People to tremble before his wonderful Power, and that he will yet afford a Day, and try them again, and that his Trumpet may once more ſound an Alarm, to the awakening of their Conſciences out of that Spiritual Slumber, wherein many are ſleeping &amp; dreaming it is well with them, and that they are Rich, and Fat, and Full, and need nothing; when their State is miſerable, and wretched, naked and bare, and undone forever, if they do not ſpeedily Repent, and return with their whole Hearts, and cry to God for Mercy, and that he will pardon their Iniquities, and heal their Back-ſlidings.</hi> Oh back-ſliding <hi>Iſrael!</hi> return, return, before it be too late, for the Lord hath long born with thee, Oh thou City of <hi>Briſtol!</hi> as the Teſtimony livingly ſprung in my Heart a little before thy Diſtreſs came upon thee, I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſay, <hi>Oh, thou City of</hi> Briſtol! <hi>a City of the Mercies of the living God, he hath highly favoured thee; thou haſt had a Day and a Time, wherein thou mightſt have Inriched thy ſelf with the Treaſures of God's Kingdom, and mightſt have grown ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might, whereby thou mighteſt have ſtood in a living Teſtimony for the Lord, with one conſent, as one Man; But now behold, the days of thy Diſtreſs are at Hand, and thy Calamity like an armed Man; and now who can bemoan thee, or who can interceed the Lord for thee? Or who can ſay to the Lord, Why haſt thou ſuffered theſe things to come to paſs? becauſe it is in his Juſtice he hath done it.</hi> And bleſſed be his Name forever, he is fulfilling the Prophecies of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whom he hath ſent early and late to proclaim his dreadful Day in that City, and Year after Year, and Moneth after Moneth, hath the Mind and Will of the Lord been declared, and Meſſenger after Meſſenger, inſomuch that many a full Stomach loathed the Honey-Comb, and all that ſeemed to received it, made not a right uſe of it; for the Lord's end, in ſending his Servants in days paſt, was,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172725:3"/>that his People might be fitted and prepared, that a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or a Deſtruction ſhould not come upon his Children at unawares, but that they ſhould believe the Teſtimonies of his Truth, and take warning by it, and amend their Lives, and be bowed in Spirit, and humbled under the great God of Heaven and Earth, that your Prayers in this ſtate might aſcend unto the long provoked God, whoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is waxen hot, and nothing will appeaſe his Anger, but true Repentance, and that with ſpeed, and true broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart: Oh! is this your ſtate? Or are you this day trampling upon the Teſtimonies of Truth, and upon the Sufferings of your dear Brethren and Siſters, that are Sufferers this day for the Teſtimony of Jeſus, and are cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed? Oh! can you forget theſe things? Come, put your Hands to the Work, and your Shouldiers to the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and cry mightily unto the Lord to ſpare a little, and give a little time to renew your ſtrength in him, that you may do ſomething for the Lord, though but at the laſt Hour; for ſurely Friends, the laſt Hour to many is very near; and the long invited, if they miſs of this Hour, they will never have another Hour to work for the living God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is my Soul concerned, and my Heart pained within me, and ſhortneſs of time is much before me, and therefore I beg it of you, that you will lay it to Heart, before it be too late, and conſider how ſoon the Lord can call for your Breath; for our Lives here are likened to the Flower of the Field, as the Lord ſaid to his Prophet, when he ſaid, <hi>What ſhall I cry? Cry, All Fleſh is Graſs, and the Glory thereof as the Flower of the Field:</hi> And I pray, how ſoon is that wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and the Beauty of it comes to nought? And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſo, why will People run the hazard of their poor Souls, for that which will augment to their perpetual Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, World without end.</p>
            <p>Oh! the Lord grant me my Requeſt, and bow his Ear to my Prayer, for I am very earneſt with the Lord, and my Heart is pained within me in your behalf: Oh! it is you, it it you that ſhould have been as <hi>Pillars in the Houſe of the Lord,</hi> that the weakeſt might have leaned upon you, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172725:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>your Courage and Valour might have apppeared in the light of the Weak, that they might have been encouraged by it, that the Strong and the Weak might have gone up together to the Mountain of the Houſe of the Lord, where the Lord would have taught you of his Ways, and you might have walked in his Paths, and he would have fortified you with Might, Courage, Strength, and Valour, and your Bow would have abode in his ſtrength, ſo that you would have grown ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might, which he would have given unto you in a bountiful manner, had you wholly given up your ſelves, and all that God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty had given you, and gave way to that noble Spirit that was in <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> who were reſolved to follow the Lord, they and their Families. Oh <hi>Friends!</hi> I can hardly write what ariſeth in my Heart, as touching this matter; but in the fear of the Lord I have this to ſay, Your Eyes ſhould have ſeen the Wonders of the Lord in a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous manner, as they did that thus leaned upon the Lord, and truſted in his ſtrength, and believed in him, and then all things were poſſible; and by obeying of the Command of the Lord the Walls of <hi>Jeriche</hi> fell, but if they had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with Fleſh and Blood, or thought the Inſtruments too mean, or conſulted with reaſoning, they had never ſeen the Power of the Lord to do his Work, neither ſhall any now this day, that reaſon with Fleſh and Blood: No, no; firſt learn Obedience, give up to obey the Lord, and then your Eyes ſhall ſee the bleſſed Work of the Lord to be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in its due time; for he is God Almighty, and All ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, therefore let every Heart confide in his Power.</p>
            <p>So, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> keep your Hearts with all diligence, for out of it are the Iſſues of Life; for we all well know, that the People that live moſt Chaſte, keep neareſt to the Lord, and they that are neareſt, hear moſt of his Counſel: And truly <hi>Friends,</hi> the time is at hand, when all ſhall be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed for the Lord, and the moſt Faithful will not ſpare of the heavenly Oyl, then it will be too late for any to go to buy. Oh! it often riſeth in my Heart, that yet a little time, and Time unto many will be no more, for which my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172725:4"/>Soul is more concerned than for any outward Suffering; for ſurely <hi>Friends,</hi> it is in my Heart to believe, that the great God of Heaven and Earth, who hath been long provoked, and tryed many waves, and ſhaken his Rod over this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion many a time, and nothing will prevail, therefore will he ariſe in his Strength, and go through this Nation, and will plague the Inhabitants thereof, he will bring Terror and Amazement upon them, that none ſhall be able to deliver out of his Hand; for he hath long called, and they have not regarded; he hath long held out his Hand, and they have not laid it to Heart, and therefore will their Calamity come at a day unawares; and becauſe they have not regarded the Call of the Lord, when they cry aloud to him, he will not regard them; Oh! then bleſſed eternally, and happy for evermore will all them be, that have obeyed the Lord in their Day, and have not their Portion with the Wicked.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So with my endeared Love unto you, and that beyond utterance, Deſiring and Praying for your Souls Proſperity, I remain your Loving Friend,</hi> Elizabeth Stirredge.</signed>

               <date>
                  <hi>The 2d Day of the 1ſt. Moneth,</hi> 1683.</date>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>For the <hi>Friends</hi> that have been ſlack in their Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Lord, in this day of Tryal, wherein they ſhould have doubled their Diligence unto the Lord, that the Lord and his Truth might have been honoured, as it was by his Servant <hi>Daniel,</hi> who believed in his God, when the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord were made to confeſs, that he was the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Living God.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172725:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO you that have been Profeſſors of the Truth of God in the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> a weighty concern hath been up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, in the fear of the Lord to warn you that have made a profeſſion of God and Chriſt, and to be Chriſts greateſt Friends, that you may take heed, that you be not found this day his greateſt Enemies to his Croſs, which is the Power of God unto Salvation; for if we that have made a profeſſion to wait upon God and Chriſt in the pure ſilence of all fleſh, at the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be endued with Power from on High, ſhould now break Chriſts Commandments, and ſhould not obey him in his requirings, then how ſhall we know his Doctrine and Life? then how ſhall Gods Enſign be ſet up to the Nations, and his Standard of Righteouſneſs to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? How ſhall they be gathered unto the Brightneſs of his Riſing, and to his great and Glorious Appearance, from off the barren Mountains, and dry Hills, where they have been ſeeking the living amongſt the dead, and ſcattered up and downn as Sheep without a Shepherd, if we that have known the Lord do not glorifie him as God, and let our Light ſhine to the Nations? For though the Candle of the Wicked is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten put out, yet it is not ſo with the Righteous, who keep in the Juſt mans path, which is a burning &amp; a ſhining Light; for it burns up all the combuſtable matter that lies in their way, and ſhines round about them to expel all darkneſs, and to make manifeſt every appearance of Evil, that we may ſhun it; and it ſhines more and more (unto them that obey it) unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day, and then ſuch can look into the perfect Law of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, the Ark of Gods Covenant, and not be deſtroyed nor conſumed; for it is <hi>the pure in Heart</hi> that ſhall <hi>ſee God</hi> and live, but the <hi>Wicked</hi> ſhall not be <hi>able to abide</hi> the notable day of his coming, neither shall they be able to ſtand in Judgment with him; for when God ſpeaks, all fleſh muſt keep Silence before him; O therefore, prepare, prepare to meet thy God, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and bring thy works before-hand to Judgment, leſt thou and thy works be burnt up together? For <hi>Sion muſt be redeemed through Judgment, and her converts cloathed with Righteouſneſs,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172725:5"/>for with the Spirit of Judgment and the Spirit of Burning, will the Lord purge away the filth of the daughter of Sion,</hi> and he will have a clean People, zealous of good Works; for Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works is Dead, as the Body is dead without the Spirit; and that Faith which doth give victory over the World, is the true Faith, which is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen; therefore did the Apoſtle exhort them in his day, to come up in the <hi>true Faith,</hi> and to put on <hi>the whole armour of God,</hi> that they might be able to <hi>ſtand againſt all the Wiles of the Devil,</hi> in the evil day, and ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done all to ſtand with their <hi>loins girt about with Truth,</hi> and ſo having on the <hi>breſt plate of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and their <hi>feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of Peace,</hi> and above all, taking the <hi>ſhield of Faith,</hi> wherewith they might be able to <hi>Quench all the fiery darts of the Wicked;</hi> for the travel of the Righteous in all Ages, was that they might know and witneſs the true paſſage through the great <hi>Tribulations</hi> within, &amp; the Enemies of the Lord ſubdued in their own Houſes; and then they did not queſtion Gods ſufficiency in bringing down their outward Enemies; for ſuch that have given up their Souls &amp; Bodies to ſerve the Lord, can truſt him with the leſſer as well as the greater; for of how much more value is the Soul than the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? for the Body is but for a little moment of time, and is cut down and returns to the duſt from whence it came; but the Soul paſſeth into the never ending day of Eternity, where the Souls of the Righteous ſhall forever live with the Lord in everlaſting Joy and Felicity, but the Wicked in everlaſting Wo and Miſery! Oh, therefore, what great need have we, while we are in theſe Earthly Tabernacles, to bring forth Fruits meet for Repentance, and to work out our Salvation with fear and trembling, that our calling and election may be made ſure with the Lord; for what have we to do whilſt in the Body, but to fear God, and keep his Commandments, which is the whole Duty of man; and bleſſed be the Name of the Lord, can a Remnant ſay, <hi>When he doth enlarge our Hearts, that his Commandments are not grievous, but joyous, and his way a way of Pleaſantneſs, and all his paths Peace!</hi> O, therefore, you that would be counted Friends of God, and Diſciples of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172725:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt, come away (whilſt the call of the Lord laſteth) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to faithfulneſs, and leave your Nets and Entanglements in this Life, which keeps you a fiſhing after the things of this World, which do periſh in the uſing, &amp; take up the daily <hi>Croſs</hi> of Chriſt, as the true Diſciples did, and follow him, that he may make you Fiſhers of men; for thoſe that will be Chriſts Diſciples muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Self, and take up the daily Croſs of Chriſt, and follow him through the great Tribulations, whereſoever he leads them; then ſuch may be made Inſtruments in the hand of the Lord, when they are converted to ſtrengthen their weak Brethren, and to teach Tranſgreſſors his Ways, that Sinners may be converted to the Truth; for the Lord did not call us into his Vineyard to ſtand Idle, but to work, and eſpecially at this time of day; now the Name of the Lord is ſo much prophaned amongſt the <hi>Heathen,</hi> by ſome that have left their publick Teſtimony to ſave Self, and have not done as holy <hi>Daniel</hi> did, <hi>notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King's Decree, he worſhipped his God as at other times, with his Windows open towards</hi> Jeruſalem; but if <hi>Daniel</hi> had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with Fleſh and Blood, <hi>That the ſame God that could hear in publick, can hear in private;</hi> and ſo shut up for fear of man, till the King's Decree was over, where had <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Deliverance been, and <hi>Gods</hi> All-ſufficiency ſeen? Oh, therefore, what have you been a doing in your ſecret Chambers for the Lord, that it cannot yet appear on the houſe top, but are ready to ſay within your ſelves, <hi>That you have not left your Teſtimony for the Truth, but do meet often together in his fear?</hi> O! ariſe, ariſe, &amp; come away; for your <hi>Reſt</hi> is <hi>polluted,</hi> for the <hi>Lord</hi> loaths your <hi>ſolemn Aſſemblies,</hi> and <hi>rejects</hi> all <hi>your Sacrifices,</hi> becauſe it is not of his own prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; <hi>therefore it is an Abomination in his ſight,</hi> &amp; it is no more than <hi>the cutting off a Dogs neck,</hi> or the <hi>offering of Swines Blood;</hi> for the Lord is jealous for his own Names ſake, which you ſhould have honour'd in the fight of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> if you had poſſeſt what you have profeſt; for what excuſe can you make with the Lord, O ye <hi>Rich men of the Earth!</hi> when the Lord ſhall enter into <hi>Judgment</hi> with you, for his great Name's ſake, which you ſhould have ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in the ſight of the People; for it was not ſufficient for the poor Woman, when she was healed by Chriſt's Virtue, of her bloody Iſſue, (which all the <hi>Phyſicians of no value</hi> could not do) to ſlip away, and not make known his Power; but she was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172725:6"/>made, at the call of Jeſus, to come and reverence him in the ſight of the Multitude, and to confeſs unto his Power, which was beyond the ſight of all Viſibles; and thoſe that followed him no further than for what they could ſee in his viſible Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, or to receive from him, to ſerve their own ends in the outward, and not only and alone for eternal Life, could not with all their thronging and preſſing of him, fetch one drop of Virtue from him, to the ſaving of their Souls. Oh! therefore take warning, and anſwer the end of the Lord with his own this day, or elſe it will be more tolerable for the <hi>Profeſſors of the times,</hi> (except you Repent, than for you) which never ſaw their way to wait upon the Lord <hi>in the ſilence of all fleſh,</hi> without they had an outward Teacher: And what if the Lord should enter into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with you, and require their Blood at your hands; for there are many honeſt-hearted amongſt them, that if they knew the Truth, they would walk in it, and gladly receive it; and the day is at hand, that they that do not gather with Chriſt, <hi>with the Whirlewind of his Wrath, they ſhall be ſcattered; and then ſhall the gathering of the People be unto him, from the</hi> Eaſt, Weſt, North <hi>and</hi> South, <hi>and from the four Winds of Heaven, and ſhall ſit down with</hi> Abraham, Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>in the Kingdom, and the Children of the Kingdom, that have lived in diſobedience be caſt out; for thoſe that have been firſt, may be laſt, and the laſt firſt</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, therefore, while you have an hour to work in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, be diligent in his Work; for curſed is every one that doth the Work of the Lord negligently! Oh, therefore, while the laſt hour laſteth, be diligent, that you may be cloathed with the <hi>Wedding Garment</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and behold the Lord and live; for the long ſuffering day of the Lord is almoſt at an end with many, and the day of his Judgments near to be poured out upon the Rebellious; then the Rebellious in <hi>Iſrael</hi> may ſay, Oh, that we had given up our all, and truſted the Lord in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, that we might have ſeen his great ſufficiency, and his holy Arm made bare for our Deliverance; then will many be ready to cry out like old <hi>Iſrael, We will go up to the Land which the Lord promiſed us:</hi> Oh! then it will be too late; for what was the anſwer of <hi>Moſes</hi> to them? <hi>Go not up for you would not go up in the Lords time, and therefore he is departed from you; and now if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172725:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>you go up, your Enemies ſhall prevail over you.</hi> Oh! therefore, you that have been called by the Name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> do not reaſon away your ſtrength, as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and they did, and give it into the hands of ſtrangers, and then let your Oppreſſors rule over you; but be tender of the Glory of God, and have true cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the ſeed of God in your own Boſoms; and then you shall be far from Oppreſſion; for the Lord hath long waited to be gracious, and his tender Compaſſion ſails not to his People; nor there is no occaſion to be offended in the Truth, whatever hath happened amongſt ſome that have profeſt it: Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord, Truth is clear in it ſelf, and without variableneſs, or ſhadow of turning, and more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable to the Faithful than ever it was; for the more we wait upon God, the more our ſtrength is renewed in him, and as we grow up in the Faith, and wait for the <hi>bleſſed Appearance of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> when he doth appear, we can ſee him as he is, and appear with him in Glory, and grow up from ſtrength to ſtrength, and from one degree of Grace to another, till we come to the fullneſs of the Statute, that is to be attained in him; and he is glorifying his People more &amp; more, and cloathing of them with his own Righteouſneſs, ſo that the Upright in heart can ſay, <hi>O Lord! thou art our Righteouſneſs, and by thy Name do we acknowledge thee; and becauſe thou haſt waſht us, therefore have we a part in thee, and thou in us; and worthy, worthy is our God to be waited upon, and to be had in everlaſting Remembrance of all his Saints that are about him, and to be reverenced and worſhipped in the beauty of Holineſs, in the Aſſemblies of his People; for his Glory is far above &amp; over all the glory of</hi> Egypt, <hi>to thoſe that ſee him as he is in his inviſible Appearance.</hi> And ſo, the deſire of my Soul is, that all the Lord's People may be gathered into the Covenant of Life and Light, and grow up in the Life and Power of Holineſs, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Declarations of Words, and ſhall remain when Words may ceaſe, and Declarations may have an end; but the Word of the Lord endures forever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So I remain your Loving Friend, Priſoner to</hi> Bridewell, <hi>for Truths Teſtimony.</hi> Dorcas Dole.</signed>
               <date>The 30th Day of the 3d Moneth, 1683.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:172725:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Lord! by a high Hand, and a ſtretched out Arm didſt thou bring the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and made a High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for thy ranſom'd ones to paſs over through the great Deep, &amp; ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up their Enemies quick, that perſued after them, ſo that they ſung thy Praiſe upon the Banks of Deliverance: but O Lord! how ſoon did they forget thy great Name and glorious Deliverance, when they met with other Difficulties, for the tryal of their Faith, as if thy Arm was ſhortned that it could not ſave them, or thy Ear heavy that thou couldſt not hear them: O! help thy People in this day, that we may take warning by their Fall, and follow thee fully through all Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, that thou mayeſt honour thy great Name in us, in making known thy great Sufficiency in the ſight of the Heathen. O Lord! let us not look back again into <hi>Egypt,</hi> for Graves to bury thy holy Seed in bondage, but raiſe us up more and more in the Reſurrection of thy Life and Power, that the ſecond Death may have no Power over us: O! thou that never ſlumbereſt nor ſleepeſt, who waſt <hi>Iſrael's</hi> Keeper, and <hi>Jacob's</hi> Preſerver in Straits and great Difficulties, watch over thy People for good, and help us to Watch and Pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually unto thee, in the motion of thy eternal Spirit; for of our ſelves we can do nothing, but when thou doſt enlarge our Hearts in and through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, we are able to perform an acceptable Sacrifice unto thee; for it is the Breath of Life which thou doſt breathe upon our Souls, which makes us in the living ſenſe of thy quickning Power, to return unto thee that which is thy due, all Honour, Praiſes &amp; true Thanks-giving, for unto thee it doth belong, and to the Lamb that ſits upon the Throne from me, and all that know thee. O! there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fill our Hearts and Souls with thy living Preſence, that our Souls may ſtill live to Praiſe thee; for thou art worthy to have all Praiſe, Honour and Renown, from the riſing of the Sun to the ſetting of the ſame; <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>☞ <hi>The Way to Health, long Life and Happineſs:</hi> Or, A diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Temperance, and the particular <hi>Nature of all things</hi> requiſit for the Life of Man; very neceſſary for all Families. The like never before publiſhed. Printed and Sold by <hi>Andrew Sowle,</hi> at the <hi>Crooked-Billet</hi> in Hollway-Lane, in <hi>Shoreditch.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
